Guide to the Samuel Ryan Curtis Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Samuel Ryan Curtis Papers
1846-1866
WA MSS 122-125
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1
(2 boxes)
The collection contains correspondence between Gen. S. R. Curtis and his family while in military service or on engineering jobs, his official correspondence with copies of orders, telegrams, and other military papers while serving in the Mexican and Civil Wars, as Indian Commissioner to make treaties with the Sioux in Montana and Dakota and while working on the Union Pacific Railroad. Family letters also record Samuel Stephen Curtis's experiences prospecting in California, 1858-60.
Curtis, Samuel Ryan, 1805-1866
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Please consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
SAMUEL RYAN CURTIS (1805-1866)
Samuel Ryan Curtis was born in New York State on February 3, 1805 and moved with his family to Licking County, Ohio, in 1809. After graduation from West Point in 1831, he was sent to Fort Gibson with the 7th Infantry. On November 3, 1831, Curtis married Belinda Buckingham of Mansfield. In the summer of 1832, he resigned his commission, returned to Ohio, was employed as an engineer on the construction of the National Road, and took up the study of law. After service in the Mexican War, he went to Iowa as chief engineer for improvements in the Des Moines River, was city engineer of St. Louis, and became interested in railroading. He represented the First Congressional District of Iowa from 1856 to 1861, interesting himself especially in the promotion of the Pacific Railroad. He resigned his seat in Congress in August, 1861, to report for duty to Major General Frémont at St. Louis. He commanded the victorious Union Army at Pea Ridge, Arkansas, in 1862, and, as a result, was given command of the Department of Missouri. Curtis was later removed on account of friction between civil and military authorities. In 1864, he was assigned to command the Department of Kansas and in 1865 was sent to the Department of the Northwest. After the Civil War, he was one of the commissioners to treat with the Indians along the Missouri, and also served on the commission to examine and report on the construction of the Union Pacific Railroad. While engaged on this survey, he died at Council Bluffs in 1866.
Both of General Curtis' sons served in the Civil War. Major Henry Zarah Curtis was assistant adjutant general on his father's staff while the latter was in command of the Department of Missouri. He was later transferred to General Blunt's staff in Kansas. He was killed in 1863 by guerrillas under Quantrill. A second son, Samuel Stephen Curtis, was aide-de-camp on his father's staff during the campaign in Arkansas and major of the 2d Colorado Regiment.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of General Curtis' intimate letters to his wife and children written at frequent intervals when he was away from them, as well as letters written to Curtis by his wife and sons. The collection also contains Curtis' official correspondence, with copies of orders, telegrams, etc., dating from his service in the Mexican and Civil Wars and on the Indian Commission which made treaties with the Sioux.
The papers consist of 416 items and are arranged in four sections. The first section (WA MSS 122) consists of autobiographical material from the years 1846-60 and includes such items as family letters and papers covering Curtis' service in the Mexican War, Curtis' work on engineering projects in Iowa and Missouri, and his term in Congress as representative from Iowa. Some of the material deals with Curtis' efforts on behalf of the Pacific Railroad. A letter to Secretary of War John Buchanan Floyd is located in this first section.
The second section (WA MSS 123) consists of letters written during the years 1858-60. This correspondence concerns the discovery of gold in Colorado, specifically Samuel Stephen Curtis' experiences going to Colorado by ox team, his experiences prospecting and trading at Cherry Creek, the early settlement of Auraria and Denver, and the attempt to establish Jefferson Territory.
The third section (WA MSS 124) consists of material from the Civil War period, 1861-65, and includes official correspondence of Major General Samuel Ryan Curtis, of the Departments of Missouri, Kansas, and the Northwest, as well as field orders, telegrams, reports, and other military papers of Major Samuel Stephen Curtis while serving with the Colorado Volunteers, and the military papers of Henry Zarah Curtis. Family letters from the period 1861-65 are included in this section. (A letter, dated April 29, 1908, and addressed to J. L. Davenport, acting commissioner of pensions, is included as well). Printed forms found in this section are of interest as examples of early printing in the West.
The fourth and final section (WA MSS 125) includes papers from the years 1865-66 which concern Montana and the Dakota Territory, the Indian Commission, and the survey of the Union Pacific Railroad.
A series of letters of General Curtis, including official correspondence and letters to his wife, has been edited and published in Annals of Iowa, 1942, 3d Ser. XXIV. The originals of those letters are not in the Coe Collection but supplement those for the years 1861-62. The official reports of the Indian Commission are printed in the Report of the Commissioner of Indian Affairs, 1865, pp. 537-42, and 1866, pp. 168-76.
The following detailed list of papers in the collection can also be found on pp. 50-55 of A Catalogue of Manuscripts in the Collection of Western Americana in the Yale University Library, Mary C. Withington, ed.
Dakota Indians -- Treaties; Dakota Indians -- Government relations; Engineering -- Iowa; Engineering -- Missouri; Gold mines and mining -- California; Gold mines and mining -- Colorado; Mexican War, 1846-1848; Colorado -- History -- To 1876; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Military orders -- United States; Reports -- United States; Engineers -- Iowa; Engineers -- Missouri; Soldiers -- United States; Curtis, Belinda Buckingham; Curtis, Cornelia; Curtis, Henry Zarah, d. 1863; Curtis, Sadie; Curtis, Samuel Ryan, 1805-1866; Curtis, Samuel Stephen; Halleck, H. W. (Henry Wager), 1815-1872; Harlan, James, 1820-1899; Mills, James K.; Sully, Alfred, 1821-1879; Curtis family; United States Commission to Negotiate with the Indians along the Upper Missouri River; United States. Army. Colorado Cavalry Regiment, 2nd (1863-1865); United States. Army. Colorado Cavalry Regiment, 3rd (1864); United States. Army. Department of Kansas; United States. Army. Department of the Missouri; United States. Army. Department of the Northwest
- WA MSS 122 Autobiographical material
  Scope and Contents
  Family letters and papers covering his service in the Mexican War, on engineering projects in Iowa and Missouri, as representative in Congress from Iowa and his efforts in behalf of the Pacific Railroad; and a letter to Secretary of War Floyd regarding the Utah Expedition. 1846-1860.
  CURTIS, SAMUEL RYAN.
  - Two autobiographical statements, written about 1862
    and 1864. 32 p.
  - One photo, "Gen. Curtis" 18 letters to his wife. November 26, 1847-December (Box 1, Folder 1)
    30, 1860. 66 p. The letter of December 27, 1847 to Mrs. Curtis contains a rough map, "Rapids of the Mississippi," indicating property he has bought.
  - 11 letters to his children, Henry Z., Samuel Stephen (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
    and Cornelia. March 6, 1850-December 27, 1860. 56 p.
  - Letter to L. M. Kennett, Mayor of St. Louis. July 19 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    1850. 4 p.
  - Letter to Secretary of War Floyd. January 29, 1858. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Copy. 4 p.
  - CURTIS, MRS. BELINDA. Letter to her husband. July 3, 1849. 3 p.
  - CURTIS, HENRY Z. 24 letters to members of his family. March 21[1851]-May 5, 1861. The letter to his father, March 29, 1858, contains a full-page drawing of the Missouri River for about five miles below Omaha. 103 p.
  - CURTIS, SAMUEL STEPHEN. 14 letters to members of his family. January 23,1854-April 25 [1865]. 42 p.
    - 14 letters to his mother written from Europe. (Box 1, Folder 6)
      January 17, 1865 [i.e., 1866]- January 11, 1867. 135 p.
  - TOMPKINS, DANIEL D. Two letters and invoices to Samuel R. Curtis. June 6-10, 1846. 6 p.
  - WOOL, JOHN E. Letter to Adjutant General Curtis. June 7, 1846,with a copy of a letter to Major D. D. Tompkins, June 7, 1846, and a memorandum, June 8, 1846. 3 p.
- WA MSS 123 Letters about the discovery of gold in Colorado
  Samuel Stephen Curtis' experiences going to Colorado by ox team, prospecting and trading at Cherry Creek, and during the early settlement of Auraria and Denver; and the attempt to establish Jefferson Territory, 1858-1860.
  - Five letters to his sons. May 16, 1858-October 21
    1859. 29 p.
  - CURTIS, HENRY ZARAH. Letter to his sister Sadie. September 7, 1858. 8 p. Three letters to his mother. September 24, 1858-November 6, 1859. 12 p.
  - CURTIS, SAMUEL STEPHEN. Two letters to his brother Henry. November 22, 1858
    March 28 [1860]; and a typewritten copy of a letter to Henry, November 2, 1858 that was printed in the Omaha Republican and copied in the Missouri Democrat, December 4, 1858. 9 p.
    - Letter to the editor. November 24, 1858, printed in (Box 1, Folder 1)
      the Council Bluffs Non-pareil, January 22, 1859. Typewritten copy. 2 p.
    - Three letters to his mother and father. February 8- (Box 1, Folder 1)
      September 16, 1859. 12 p.
- WA MSS 124 The Civil War period, 1861-1865.
  Official correspondence of Major General S. R. Curtis, of the Departments of Missouri, Kansas, and the North- west; field orders, telegrams, reports and other military papers of Major Samuel Stephen Curtis on the campaign of the Colorado Volunteers; military papers of Henry Z. Curtis; and family letters.
  - Map of the Battle of Pea Ridge. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    March 7 and 8, 1862. Printed. 56 x 43 cm.
  - CURTIS, SAMUEL RYAN. Letter to his daughter Sadie. April 22, 1861. 3 p. 40 letters to his wife. June 16, 1861-July 26,1865. 150 p.
    - Three letters and a telegram to Samuel S. Curtis. (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
      November 4, 1863-April 10, 1865. 10 p.
    - Two letters and a telegram to Lieutenant Colonel (Box 1, Folder 3)
      James K. Mills. April 3-7, 1862. Copies. 3 p.
    - Six telegrams to General Halleck. April 5-September (Box 1, Folder 3)
      25, 1862. 10 p.
    - Two letters to Captain W. H. McLean. April 5, 1862. (Box 1, Folder 3)
      2 p.
    - Three letters to Captain J. C. Kelton. April 19-29 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      1862. 4 p.
    - Letter to Brigadier General George W. Cullum. April (Box 1, Folder 3)
      20, 1862. 1 p.
    - Letter to Colonel Coates. October 21. 1864. "Copy." (Box 1, Folder 3)
      1 p.
    - Letter to the editors of the Cincinnati Commercial. (Box 1, Folder 3)
      August 31, 1862. "A true copy." T. I. McKenny. 1 p.
    - Memoranda-Arkansas campaign. June 6-August 31, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      April 26-28, 1863. 13 p.
  - CURTIS, MRS. BELINDA. Two letters to her husband. August 28, October 19,1864. 8 p.
  - CURTIS, HENRY Z. Telegram to his mother about Sadie's death. April 3, 1862. 1 p.
    - Orders to Major C. H. Perry and Lieutenant J. W. (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Noble. [April 6, 1862.] 1 p.
    - Telegram to Captain F. S. Winslow. April 19, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      letter, April 20, 1862. 3 p.
    - Letter to Lieutenant Luke O'Reilly. April 20, 1862. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - BALDWIN, ELIAS B. Telegram to H. Z. Curtis. [April] 4 [1862].
  - BALLINGER, RICHARD H. Letter to Major H. Z. Curtis. December 1, 1862.
    Copy. 5 p.
  - BOYD, SEMPRONIUS H. Telegram to General Curtis. April 7 [1862]. 1 p.
  - BUCKINGHAM, G. Letter to his sister, Mrs. S. R. Curtis, about
    Lincoln's death and its effect on the politicians. April 21, 1865. 4 p.
  - CHIPMAN, NORTON PARKER. Telegram to General Curtis. October 10, 1863
    announcing murder of Major Curtis.
  - FORMAN, JACOB G. Letter to Hon. Henry Wilson. [ca. November 29
    1862.] Copy. 4 p.
    - Letter to Colonel N. P. Chipman. January 20, 1863. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - HALLECK, HENRY WAGER. Eight telegrams to General Curtis. April 5, 1862-
    April 26-1863. Five with drafts of answers on same sheet. 9 p.
  - JOHNSON, P. R. Letter to Colonel Compton relating to attacks on
    Curtis. November 16, 1862. Copy. 5 p.
  - MILLS, JAMES K. Seven letters to General Curtis. April 3-8, 1862.
    7 p.
    - Telegram to H. Z. Curtis. April 6, 1862, with (Box 1, Folder 4)
      answer on same sheet. 1 p.
  - PORTER, ASBURY B. Telegram to General Curtis. [April] 6, 1862.
    Telegram, General Curtis to Colonel Boyd. April 6, 1862, on verso. 2 p.
  - STRONG, WILLIAM K. Two letters to General Curtis. "Private." November
    17, December 23, 1862. 5 p.
  - SULLY, ALFRED. Letter to General Curtis. July 25, 1865. 2 p.
  - TAYLOR, HAWKINS. Letter to General Curtis. September 19, 1864. 4 p.
  - TOWNSEND, EDWARD DAVIS. Telegram to General Curtis. January 2, 1863, with
    answer on verso.
  - WASHBURN, CADWALLADER C. Letter to General Curtis. "Private." September 13
    1862. 1 p. Certified, a true copy. T. I. McKenny.
  - WINSLOW, FREDERICK S. Letter to General Curtis. July 3, 1863. 3 p.
  - CURTIS, SAMUEL STEPHEN. Commissions and discharge papers as Lieutenant
    Colonel of the 3d Regiment, Colorado Volunteers, Major, 2d Regiment of Cavalry, Colorado Volun- teers, 1862-1865, proceedings of the Council of Administration, 3d Regiment of Colorado Volun- teers, 1863; special and general orders, 1863- 1866; invoice of camp and garrison equipage, 1863
    muster-in roll of Samuel S. Curtis, 1864; receipts for books; copy of a telegram to Colonel J. H. Ford, October 8, 1865 and letter to J. L. Davenport, acting commissioner of pensions, April 29, 1908. 52 p. Some of the forms are of interest as examples of early printing in the West.
- WA MSS 125 The Dakota and Montana papers
  Indian Commission, and survey of the Union Pacific Railroad. 1865-1866. Materials are arranged by chronology within the box, not alphabetically by names, as in the following listing.
  CURTIS, S. R.
  - 68 letters to his wife. March 11, 1865-December 25
    1866. The letter of July 10, 1866 contains two small sketches. 240 p.
  - Six letters to Samuel S. Curtis. August 21-December (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    24, 1865. 17 p.
  - Telegram to General E. D. Townsend. August 4, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    and answer, August 5, 1865, signed: "T. M. Vincent, A.A.G." 2 p.
  - Four letters to E. M. Stanton, Secretary of War. (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
    September 29-October 25, 1865. Copies. 15 p.
  - Letter to Lieutenant J. O'Neill. October 10, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    and answer of the same date. Copies. 2 p.
  - Six letters to Hon. James Harlan. October 10, 1865- (Box 1, Folder 4-6)
    May 25, 1866. Copies. 28 p.
  - Two letters to Colonel Pattee. October 20, 1865, May (Box 1, Folder 6)
    16, 1866; and Pattee to Curtis, October 22, 1865. Copy. 4 p.
  - Telegram to General G. M. Dodge. October 16, 1865. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letter to Colonel E. B. Taylor. October 31, 1865. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letter to Colonel Thornton. March 13, 1866. Copy. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letter to General Sherman. March 14, 1866. Copy. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letter to Colonel [John G. Clark] commanding at Fort (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Rice. March 14, 1866. Copy. 2 p.
  - Letter to Captain Phinney. March 14, 1866. Copy. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letter to Colonel I. V. Reeve from Curtis and H. W. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Reed. May 15, 1866. Copy. 4 p.
  - Appointment of George C. Granger. May 21, 1866. 1 p. Letter to Hon. O. Guernsey. May 22, 1866. 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Memorandum of a telegraphic conversation between (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Major General Curtis and Major General G. M. Dodge. September 18, 1865. 4 p.
  - Memorandum-Agenda for the first day at Fort Sully. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    May 26, 1866. 2 p.
  - Abstract of obligations contemplated by the treaties (Box 1, Folder 6)
    entered into by the Commission...1866. 3 p.
  - U.S. COMMISSION to negotiate with the Indians along (Box 1, Folder 4)
    the Upper Missouri River. Articles of a treaty made and concluded at Fort Sully between the commission- ers on the part of the United States and the chiefs and head men of the Minneconjou Band of the Dakota or Sioux Indians. October 10, 1865. Attested a true copy by E. F. Ruth. 5 p.
  - Articles of a treaty...[with] the chiefs and head (Box 1, Folder 4/5)
    men of the Two Kettles Band of Dakota or Sioux Indians. October 19, 1865. Attested a true copy by E. F. Ruth. 5 p.
  - Signatories to all the treaties, United States (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Blackfeet, Two Kettles, Lower Brulés (Sichangu), Yanktonais (Lower), Upper Yanktonais, Sans Arcs, Minneconjous, Ogalallas, Onk-pah-pahs. A list. 11 p.
  - U.S. SECRETARY OF THE INTERIOR. [Instructions to the (Box 1, Folder 4)
    commissioners to make treaties with the Indians of the South West] Washington, August 16, 1865. Printed. 4 p.
  - CURTIS, MRS. BELINDA. Letter to her husband. July 25, 1865. 4 p. Letter to her son, Samuel S. December 26, 1866. 4 p.
  - CURTIS, SAMUEL S. Letter to his father. October 27 [1865]. 2 p.
  - BURTON, R. P., master of steamer Calypso. Letter to Brigadier General H. H. Sibley, H. W. Reed
    and E. B. Taylor. October 31, 1868. Copy [?] 1 p.
  - CLARK, JOHN G. Two letters to General S. R. Curtis. November 29
    1865, May 17, 1866. 11 p.
  - COOLEY, D. N. Letter to Hon. Newton Edmunds, Office of Indian
    Affairs, relating to the Blackfeet Indians. April 17, 1866. Copy. 3 p.
    - Two letters to General Curtis. April 25, May 8, 1866. (Box 1, Folder 6)
      4 p.
  - DODGE, GRENVILLE M. Telegram to General Curtis. [August] 28, 1865. 1 p.
  - ECKERT, THOMAS T. Letter to Hon. James Harlan. August 19, 1865. Copy.
  - EDMUNDS, NEWTON. Letter to General Curtis. September 8, 1865. 3 p. Letter to General Curtis and the Rev. H. W. Reed.
    May 19, 1866. Copy [?] 2 p.
  - GOODRICH, MOSES H. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Letter to Colonel E. B. Taylor. November 10, 1865. Two copies. 2 p.
  - GUERNSEY, ORRIN. Telegram and letter to General Curtis. September 12
    1865, May 14, 1866. 3 p.
  - HARLAN, JAMES, Secretary of the Interior. Letter to Major General S. R. Curtis. August 17
    1865, enclosing a copy of President Johnson's order, August 15, 1865, appointing commissioners to negotiate treaties with the Sioux and Cheyennes of the Upper Missouri. 3 p.
    - Five letters to General Curtis. August 17, 1865-May (Box 1, Folder 4-6)
      11, 1866. Copies of a letter and telegram from General Pope, and a telegram from General Sibley, August 16 and 18, enclosed with two of the letters. 11 p.
    - Letter to Hon. E. M. Stanton. August 16, 1865. Copy. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - HAY, JOHN. Letter to Samuel S. Curtis. January 10, 1866 [i.e.
    1867], about the death of his father. 1 p.
  - HITT, R. R. Letter to Colonel E. B. Taylor. October 28, 1865.
    Copy. 1 p.
  - MAJORS, ALEXANDER. Letter to General Curtis. July 10, 1866. 3 p.
  - NORTON, MARTIN. Letter to Colonel Taylor. November 10, 1865. Copy.
  - PLIMPTON, JOHN G. Letter to General Curtis. August 27, 1865. 1 p.
  - POPE, JOHN. Circular to officers of the Department of the
    Missouri to cooperate with the Indian Commission, signed by John T. Sprague, Colonel and Chief of Staff. August 29, 1865. Copy. 1 p.
  - REED, HENRY WALTER. Letter to Major W. S. Woods. November 10, 1865. At-
    test, "E. F. Ruth." Copy. 1 p.
    - Three letters to General Curtis. May 29-June 3 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      1866, enclosing a list of property left at Crow Creek by J. W. Stone, Agt., May 30, 1866. 5 p.
  - ROSE, ROBERT H. Letter to Indian Agent [J. W. Stone]. July 27, 1865.
  - RUTH, E. F. Letter to Captain Burton, Steamer Calypso. October
    21, 1865. Copy. 1 p.
  - SIMPSON, J. H. Telegram to General S. R. Curtis, asking him to
    serve on a commission to examine part of the Union Pacific Railroad. November 16, 1865. 1 p.
  - SULLY, ALFRED. Letter to Brigadier General H. H. Sibley. September
    22, 1865. Copy. 2 p.
    - Letter to General Curtis. October 12, 1865 [copy] (Box 1, Folder 4)
      enclosing a list of chiefs and principal men who made peace in 1863 and 1864. 3 p.
    - Order to Captain M. H. Goodridge. April 4, 1866. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - TAYLOR, EDWARD B. Letter to Governor Newton Edmunds. October 28, 1865.
    - Three letters to Captain Burton. October 29-30 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      1865. Attested true copies, by E. F. Ruth. The letters of October 29, 30, 1865 signed by Sibley, Reed and Taylor. 5 p.
    - Letter to M. H. Goodridge. November 10, 1865. Copy. (Box 1, Folder 5)
      3 p.
    - Letter to M. Norton, Esq. November 10, 1865. Copy. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - THORNTON, CHARLES C. G. Letter to General Sibley. October 9, 1865. Copy.
  - VAN VALKENBURG, ROBERT B. Letter to E. F. Ruth. August 28, 1865. Copy. 2 p. Telegram to S. R. Curtis. September 9, 1865. 1 p.